I want to talk primarily about cases that will come before a
community magistrate.
Not
exclusively,
but dealing with the profile of young person, female or
Māori.
I argue that justice
that does not recognize an offender as a moral agent
is not a good justice system.
The discussion around improvement to the
justice system in recent times
has been about making social variables part of the
assessment in terms of crime and criminality.
What has become more prevalent
has been the increased dependence on the recognition of
particular social, cultural, and political
context. I argue that where these elements enter into
decisions with regard conviction and
sentencings, these disrupt
the principles found in our Western system of justice
in terms of partiality and objectivity.
My observation is based on the writing of Von Hertz, his
censor-based justification for
punishment. For both repentant
or defied offenders, we would not wish to exempt
from blame for either. Both remain moral
agents,
limiting inquiry to questions about his or her choice to
make rational choices.
So I would oppose a view that deemed a group as
being unable to make rational choices.
In the case involving a truck driver in Taranaki killed by a
13-year-old female using his own hammer,
there have been attempts to revisit the crime by lawmakers looking
at variables such as age,
developmental stage, and cognitive function.
Other cases I will mention is the conviction of sexual offenses
by Jayden Meyer, amongst others.
If people are called to desist, there must be a good reason
for supporting
it is wrong.
I'm concerned we are breeding a sense of self-entitlement
among certain offenders. This is, "I can put myself above others,"
and I argue this is setting up a dangerous precedent
in making concessions to popular opinion of
writers such as Leffa.
Treating an actor as someone capable of choice rather than a circus
tiger is a matter of acknowledging his dignity as a human
being.
And while we can have some confidence in the moral judgment that offenders
should be treated as agents capable of choice,
this will not
guarantee that this would lead to a more smooth-running
society, nor even a
society with more social cohesion.
But I reject the notion that it should come at a cost
of the case of justice that I am presenting.
Thank you, Max.
Rima.
Thank you. Max,
you touched upon the concept of someone having
their mental capability. Do you mean the
notion that
men in particular, women to the age of about 21, but men in particular,
their brains are still developing to the age of 25?
Is that what you meant when you touched on
development?
Yes. So this has been a
thought made popular by such writers
as
Nigel Leffty, and it
has gone and infected
a lot of society. It's also affected lawmakers in
terms of how they
look at young offenders.
Yeah.
Thank you.
Thank you, Max. Thanks for your submission today.
We're now going to move to online to the Defense Lawyers
Association.
Hi, Elizabeth.
Tena koutou katoa.
Thank you very much for joining us. We've got you down for 10 minutes.
We've read your written submission-
Yeah
... and just leave some time at the end for questions, please.
Yes, of course. I won't take 10 minutes at all.
Thank you so much for the opportunity to speak in relation to the Community
Magistrate Legislation Amendment Bill.
As you know from our written submission, Te Matakāhi, the Defense Lawyers
Association,
is a organization that represents criminal defense lawyers
and their clients in terms of changes in the
criminal justice landscape that may impact on
access to justice, fairness, accountability,
and a humane and safe approach to criminal matters.
The bill is largely supported by Te Matakāhi
in terms of particularly the overall gain of reducing delay and
making better use of judicial resources.
We don't oppose steps that could achieve that
safely. There is one clause in particular that we do oppose,
and that's Clause 22, and the written submission focuses on
the opposition to that portion of the
proposed bill.
I also, of course, have read the submissions that have been
put forward by the New Zealand Law Society and the
Law Association and other legal bodies, and also speak in
support of concerns around the amendments to sections
14 to 17 of the Bail Act,
and where guilty pleas to Category 3
offenses Would be contemplated in the reservations that are
listed there by the New Zealand Law Society in particular.
If I can though address in
the speaking slot now the concerns that we hold around Clause 22,
and the concerns come from a number of different
angles and perspectives. We are concerned that
the impression that is left about New Zealand's Criminal Justice
System will be impeded if we have non-legally trained
fact finders sitting essentially as judges as community
magistrates.
The concept that just because the maximum
penalty for something is three months or
under means that it's simple and
straightforward, is a misnomer. Some of the
most complicated issues that affect criminal
justice are charges that are,
on the face of it, not that serious, but do engage real
issues, and our very strong concern is that
community magistrates
have a very strong place in our criminal justice system, yes, but their place
should not be in determining guilt of people
where the maximum penalty is still one that
carries imprisonment.
And whilst, of course, people can have courses and
training, and we recommend and of course support all of that,
the reality is that there would be an inconsistent approach
taken to the judicial background
of different judicial officers in New Zealand.
Family court associates must have seven years as a practicing lawyer.
Associate judges of a high court, obviously legal
experience and substantive legal experience required.
Associate coroners,
practice certificates with at least five years.
And so this reducing the threshold
for community magistrates who have no legal training necessarily
is a deep concern with the perception of justice and the delivery of
justice.
Our concern is that this impedes
on Section 25A of the New Zealand Bill of Rights Act in terms of a fair
hearing before an independent and impartial court.
But also New Zealanders are entitled to expect that judicial
officers are legally trained, and
by allowing Clause 22 to pass, you are
essentially saying that that is not so.
And you just have to step back, I think, as well, and think how members of the
public will look at that. If someone has been convicted and sentenced to
imprisonment by a community magistrate, the first thing that they will be saying
is, "Well, this is
rubbish. The person wasn't even a lawyer.
They didn't even have a law degree, and now they're going to send me to jail."
So I think there's a real concern about,
yes, we need efficiency in the criminal justice space, and yes, there's lots in the
bill that reduces the burden on judges,
and allowing CMs to have greater scope to take care of
administrative matters. Absolutely no problem with that.
But this Clause 22 is problematic.
And of course, the downstream or the perception of cost
savings is also an illusion because all you're doing
is shoving the problem down through into appeals,
judges having to get involved, and in the process of doing
that, you are undermining the reputation of New Zealand's criminal justice
system.
So while we're very supportive of large portions of the bill,
Clause 22 in particular we see as a very dangerous and
unwise inclusion in the bill, and we share our other legal
professional organizations that also express the same concern.
And as I say, also raise a concern around
guilty plea,
particularly where it's tied to bail with the community magistrate
and the way that the Sections 14 to 17 of the Bail
Act and the Category 3 guilty plea in Clause 24
is referenced. The Law Society raises the point
that there is a concern that you will be incentivizing people to
plead guilty, and the problems with that are well known and the Chief
Justice is incredibly concerned about that
happening in New Zealand, and no good comes from it.
No good comes from it in terms of our reputation, for the parties involved,
or for the cost of undoing and unwinding those
sorts of errors. So those are the comments that I'd have to make.
I'm obviously very happy to answer any questions
that the committee has.
Thank you, Elizabeth. We've got a question from Dan Rosewarne.
Yes, thank you so much.
Yeah, thanks, Elizabeth. You mentioned so a maximum penalty is not a measure
of trial complexity-
Correct
... and you highlight that it's particularly obvious in driving matters.
Mm-hmm.
And I was just wondering if you could, for my own understanding, give me a
particular driving charge where that might be applicable?
Well, that's the difficult aspect to it,
Mr. Rosewarne, because I think that what looks like it might be
straightforward from the outside can be very fact
specific and can become very complex very
quickly. There are lawyers in New Zealand, as you will know, that
specialize in traffic matters because of the
complexity that's involved in traffic
legislation and in some of the factual issues that arise and the
circumstances that arise. So as much as I'd like to give you
a short form, "Look, you should look at this section and this section, and these
are the types of offenses I'm talking about," that actually isn't,
I think, the right way to look at it, as much as I want to be helpful.
Because we often find that you go down to
court for something that you think is reasonably open and shut, and the next
minute you are knee-deep in access to justice,
human rights issues- And before you know it, you're in the Court of Appeal.
So,
I just think that--
and the danger here that's engaged is that we're
talking about imprisonable offenses,
and that's the problem.
We didn't have as much opposition when community magistrates were
doing judge alone, well,
judicial officer alone trials,
where it was finable only,
because there'd be time for review and someone's liberty wasn't at stake.
But where liberty is at stake, it really does, as we say, where the rubber
hits the road, and that's where we've got to be super careful.
And as I say, as a practitioner for almost 30 years now,
I've certainly gone down to court for what I thought would be something that on
paper looks relatively straightforward, and neck
minute, you're not straightforward at all.
So, yeah. Sorry I can't be more helpful-
No, that's, no, you're-
... or far outs, but that's kind of the point that I'm making about that.
Thank you. Okay, and we've got a question from Camilla Belich.
Thanks for your submission.
Thank you.
I just had a question around, I think the point about
liberty is important. The issue that I wanted to
get your guidance on is, at the moment I understand we've got around 23
community magistrates and only about eight of them are legally qualified, and
I'm not sure if they would be to the extent I think you may have suggested,
seven years for comparable PQE. But
the... And I don't know whether they would fall under that or not.
But,
so would a proposal
to kind of further the objective of this legislation, but taking
into account your concerns, would you
see that if these new powers were only available to those that were
legally qualified and the other community magistrates did the other work, would
that be a workable
solution, or do you-
I'm not sure. I'm not sure, Ms. Belich.
I think the problem would be
how that judicial resource would then get managed, and then
whether you'd end up with a two-tiered approach where you have a community
magistrate in, Whangarei that has legal
training, but a community magistrate...
The community magistrate that covers Wellington Lower Hutt and Porirua comes from a
real estate background and has no legal training.
So, then it would become a little bit postcode justice depending
on where you were and where your community magistrate
sat from.
Can I just have a supplementary question on that?
So,
we have been advised that
a way that currently
the magistrates lists work is that, because there is a,
I can't remember the exact name, is it chief magistrate or the head magistrate-
Mm
... is able to tailor the lists depending on people's
expertise.
Do you have any reflections on whether that's,
with these new changes, whether that's likely to be effective in mitigating
any of those concerns?
I don't, because you're still working from the same
pool of numbers and the same small proportion that have
legal training. And I think your question might point about,
well, what level of legal training, and is there a guidelines and
guidance in terms of maybe it should be a certain
amount of PQE, and an experience in litigation or an
experience in criminal or
jurisdiction that might be important there.
So,
if we had a situation where community magistrates had legal training and had met
a standard of PQE, and there was the complaint process that
extended as well to community magistrates, as I know the Law Society has
suggested in their submission, then that might alleviate some of the concerns.
Absolutely. Because the concern is that you've got non-legally trained people
exercising the power to imprison.
But unless we had that change,
I'm afraid my position would still be that we should just not extend
Clause 22, and that maybe it's something that we come back to if the
community magistrates
become people who are legally trained.
Thank you.
Thank you, Elizabeth. Really appreciate your time this afternoon and your written
submission as well.
Thank you so much.
Thanks. Okay, now we've got Community Law Centres Aotearoa, and they're
joining us online as well.
Hey, Karen. Thank you for joining us this afternoon.
Hello.
We have read your written submission, and we've got you down for 10 minutes.
Over to you.
Great. Thank you. I'm just checking if Jo...
I'm meant to be here with Jo Turner, but I'm not sure if she's online yet.
No, it doesn't.
Well, I will get going, and we'll see-
Thank you
... what happens. Tena koutou,
members of the committee. Tena koe, Mr. Chair.
Thank you for this opportunity to submit today.
You'll know that I'm Karen Hutchinson, as written down.
I'm a law reform coordinator at CLCA, which means that I take all the feedback from
our community lawyers on the ground and bring that to you,
as select committee on changes to the law.
I'm here with
Jo Turner. I can see that she is there.
I am here. I'm just having-
Let me pull up Jo
... some technical problems, sorry.
That's okay. I'm here with Jo, and she is a solicitor at
Otago Community Law and has extensive
experience in criminal law as a criminal lawyer.
I'll summarize our submissions and leave time for questions.
We are the national body that coordinates and advocates for 24 community law
centers across the country. Community law centers routinely provide
initial legal advice on criminal law matters, and some of our lawyers do criminal
defense work.
It's number three on the areas of work that community lawyers
do in our movement after employment and care of children.
We agree that measures are needed to improve timeliness across the district
court, but our submissions outline that we're concerned that access to justice is
compromised in the pursuit of timeliness in this bill.
We made some high-level submissions on the bill on the following points.
Our experience is that community magistrate days in the district court are really
heavy in terms of workload and long waits,
and understand that there's a few more magistrates potentially on the
way. But we've recommended that if there is to be greater work,
then there needs to be some more time for them to sit.
The bill, in our view, essentially moves that chunk of
work, the backlog that's sitting there, or the
clog that's sitting there from judges to community magistrates without
making more room for them. Increasing capacity and
speed at this part of the criminal justice system is likely to create
pressure on other parts of the system, prosecutors,
corrections, legal aid and duty lawyers.
And
I note too, I've just seen from the chief judge's
submission that
she's recommended that there be a first principles review for increasing capacity
in the district court. That sounds like a
really comprehensive way forward rather than addressing things in this way with
this bill.
Similar to the previous submitter,
Ms. Hall, you'll know not all community magistrates are required to hold
a legal qualification and have practice experience.
This is of real concern to us in relation to Clause 22,
for increased jurisdiction to preside over Category 2 offenses with a
term of imprisonment not exceeding three months.
For this reason in particular,
the
presumption or the ... Sorry, the perception of what that will look
like for our criminal justice system and also any difficulties that are
encountered in terms of
the expertise and the skill and the judgment that's required,
and any missteps in those ways is likely to
affect those groups that are over-represented, including Maori and
Pacifica people. We have concerned about the expanded bail
jurisdiction, given that ultimately that decision rests with
a judge at the moment, and we don't believe that those decisions
should be extended.
We support the appointment of a principal community magistrate,
and that they must be a district court judge.
We wonder whether that should be an additional district court judge
rather than trying to put that job on a district court judge, given how busy
they are.
Given the access to justice issues raised in our submissions and by others,
including The Law Society, TLANZ, Te Hunga Roa
Maori,
and the defense
lawyers group before us,
there should really be a mechanism to monitor
how these
changes play out,
and that there be a statutory review if the bill is to go ahead in its
current form. And just
a point about the potential for community magistrates
to need to be required to hold legal qualifications should these
extended powers go ahead.
Family court associates
and other judicial officers need to have those
qualifications, and we believe that in this situation, they should have those
qualifications as well.
And that's really all I have from our submissions.
And if there's any questions, we'd love to hear them from you.
Duncan.
Kia ora.
Good to see you, as always. Thanks for all your work you do on this law reform
stuff.
I guess I want to ask a question that's kind of been
nagging away, and it's not a very polite one.
But
is there a quality problem with community
magistrates?
I understand the whole idea of giving
citizen magistrates some modest powers to direct traffic
in the district courts. But when they come to
make decisions in hard law,
are they any good at it? And you're much closer to the
coalface than I am, because I have concerns in
extending powers if what we see already is
poor quality justice kind of done on the cheap.
So it's a bit of a tough question, but I'd be really interested in an honest
answer.
I'll leave that to Jo. Do you have anything, Jo?
Yeah.
The community magistrates that come to Dunedin
are all really lovely people and do a great job,
but their ways of approaching the various issues are
quite different. They're not always
the way you would expect a judge to approach it.
So there is a difference in kind of
expertise or comfortness in that area.
Some community magistrates read
... Well, it comes across like they're reading a script.
Which can be problematic because it's all pre-written and
pre-decided.
So I think there are issues around quality, and that
really lies at our concerns around the increased jurisdiction.
When you're getting these
people to make decisions of a more serious nature, then the
risks are much higher that they get it wrong
Thanks for that. That's really useful.
Okay. Thank you very much, Karen, and thank you, Joe, as well.
Really appreciate both of you joining us this afternoon.
Thank you.
Kia ora. Ka kite.
Okay. We've got our last submission from the Law Association of New
Zealand, who are joining us online as well.
Good afternoon, all.
Hello. We can't see you at present.
Switch it up screen.
Oh, there you go. You can see me now.
Great. We've got you down for 10 minutes. We've read your written submission.
Over to you.
Thank you.
Thank you, Chair, and the members of the committee.
Of course, I appear on behalf of the Law Association.
Both the Criminal Law Committee and the Public and Administrative Law Committee
made submissions on the bill.
Look, we support the objective of the bill.
We do recognize that there's serious pressure and delays facing the District
Court. We seriously support the Chief Community
Magistrate. Judge Moses is very experienced, and we are very happy that he's been
appointed to the role, and we will support him in any capacity we
can. But there's one aspect of this bill that we
strongly oppose, and that's quite consistent with all the other associations
who have made submissions. So I really want to concentrate on that
today as opposed to all the other aspects of the bill, which we have put in
our written submissions. And Duncan, I would like you to ask me the same question
you asked other speakers in terms of
what we see on the ground, because I do have a good answer for you on that, because
we do deal with CMs quite extensively-
Well, consider it asked
... across the country.
Consider it asked.
Yes, I will answer it at the end. So
look, our main issue is around giving community magistrates
jurisdiction to preside over trials on Category 2 offendings
and determining guilt,
when the offense carries up to three months imprisonment.
I was heavily involved during the consultation process,
and during that time, we actually
said that the magistrate should not do judge-alone trials
for anything other than fine-only matters.
But once the Parliament moves beyond the fine-only
offending and allows a person who's not required to be legally
qualified to determine contested criminal guilt
for something which is imprisonable, whether it's three months or not,
we say an important constitutional and institutional boundary has been
crossed.
What
you may think is that because the offense carries up to three months
imprisonment, it doesn't mean it's necessarily simple offending.
It's actually exactly the opposite.
So-
Oh,
lost
her
I think I was-
Samira
... I think I was cut off. Can you hear me now?
We can. We lost you for the last 30 seconds.
Okay. All right. If you just give me one second, I will probably
use this other connection.
Yeah. But you can just-
Okay. Sorry
... turn your camera off. Maybe it would save some-
Maybe
... internet.
Okay. I should be all good from now. Sorry.
So I'm just going to go back a little bit, just 30 seconds.
I
was giving you an example in terms of offenses under Category 2 for
up to three months, and I was going to focus on, for example, drunk drive
offending, careless driving causing injury, or careless driving causing death.
So these type of offending, let's focus on one, which is drunk
driving. They can involve highly technical questions
concerning a statutory interpretation, procedural compliance,
evidential presumptions, admissibility, improperly obtained
evidence, identification, expert or technical
evidence of the Land Transport Act, the Evidence Act, and appellate authority.
So the judicial officer must be able to identify these
issues. And I can tell you this, even if you ask other
very experienced trial lawyers, it's a lot easier to run
a trial for an aggravated robbery or a
burglary as opposed to a three-month imprisonment drunk drive charge.
The technicality involved in these offendings
are so much that even with a District Court judge, we sometimes have to get into
statutory interpretation and explain to the judge why
this clause applies or why that clause applies.
And if you remember a few years ago over the Block J defense in a
first-time drunk drive, we had to go to the Supreme Court because that
involved a question of law. So you're not necessarily dealing with
simple offending just because it carries maximum three months
imprisonment. That is the first point that we would
raise. So the maximum penalty measures the seriousness
Parliament attaches to an offense. It doesn't measure the complexity of the trial.
So I really invite you all to get more information on how technical these
trials can get. Then we have the issue of
institutional anomaly here. So I would ask the question:
Why do we have associate employment judges, associate family court
judges, associate high court judges, and they come from a legally
qualified background with years and years in practice.
Whereas in criminal law, we are appointing people doing trials when they are
not legally qualified or where they haven't practiced at all in the past.
So that's another
point that we have raised. The point that I just
wanted to mention, which was not in our submissions, the
Regulatory impact statement from the consultation which happened in
2023,
says that imprisonment and home detention are core judicial functions that only
judges should undertake, and yet you have decided to
determining guilt
and convicting someone by way of a trial is not a core
judicial function, and it can be done by someone who's not legally
qualified. So that is a very important distinction
here that you need to be able to make.
The same RIS records that the judiciary and
other legal professionals raised substantive concerns
over the expansion of the jurisdiction of the community magistrates at the time.
I do not understand between 2023 and 2025, where
the bill has been introduced, what has changed.
Because nothing really has changed in respect of the consultation
that was conducted two years ago, three years ago, with the profession and with the
judiciary. And the profession and the judiciary all raised concerns
over the same issues, which is now implemented in the current
bill, including the magistrates presiding over judge-alone trials.
So we really don't know what has been
done to address those concerns. You're doing this to avoid a backlog,
okay? But it's going to be very counterproductive because you're going to end up
with so many appeals. So you're not going to
actually free up judges from
doing less cases. Not only they have to deal with their own cases, but now they
have to deal with appeals after appeals.
I also-
I'm just going to
say you've got about 30 more seconds.
Yeah. I'm going to cut it short.
Cut it short, because we have put most of our
objections in
our submissions, but long story short is this: as long as
you remove
the expansion of jurisdiction for them to preside over trials,
I think that potentially the rest of the objections that have been
raised by us and other associations to an extent could be addressed and could be
moderated. But there's nothing we can suggest to make
it better in terms of them presiding over a judge-alone
trial. That needs to be completely removed from the bill, and that needs to stay
with the judge.
Okay, thank you very much for your time this afternoon and for the written
submission that you submitted as well. Really appreciate it. Thank you.
No problem. Can I just quickly answer Duncan's question very
briefly in 20 seconds? Duncan, you ask how they operate on
the ground. Jo answered the question quite well.
Sometimes it comes across as they are reading from a transcript.
That means they have typed it up for themselves, and they're reading from it in
terms of giving a decision, which is kind of concerning.
It doesn't affect the fact that they're lovely people, they're really good people
to appear before. But one thing that we come across quite regularly
in court, as soon as they're out of their comfort zone, as
soon as they're out of the comfort zone in the sense that, "Oh, I don't know the
answer to this," things just get very complicated in court.
Yeah.
And then explaining to them what the law is, what the
statutory interpretation of that section is, what is the correlation between
the Land Transport Act, for example, and the Evidence Act or the Sentencing Act,
it becomes too confusing for them.
And of course, it becomes very complicated for the lawyer, which means we have to
adjourn the case and either get the matter dealt with by a judge or
try to make further submissions so they can go and talk to a district court judge
to make a decision. So,
yeah, that's the answer to your question.
Thank you for that.
Thank you.
Thank you very much.
My pleasure. Thank you, everyone.
See ya.
Thanks.
Okay, we're going to move into private now.
If our advisors come forward, please